<div type="chapter">
  <pb n="26"/>
  <head>CHAPTER IV</head>
  <head>THE GOTHIC DEVELOPMENT OF THE GENERAL GERMANIC VOWEL-SYSTEM</head>

  <div type="subchapter" n="1">
    <head>A. The Short Vowels of Accented Syllables</head>

    <div type="subsubchapter">
      <head>a</head>

      <div type="section" n="65">
        <p>
          § 65. Germanic a remained unchanged in Gothic, as Goth. dags, OE. dæg, OS. dag, OHG. tag, O.Icel. dagr, day; Goth. gasts, OS. OHG. gast, guest; Goth. fadar, OE. fæder, O.Icel. faðir, OS. fader, OHG. fater, father; Goth. ahtáu, OS. OHG. ahto, eight; Goth. OE. OS. OHG. faran, O.Icel. fara, to go; Goth. OE. OS. band, OHG. bant, he bound, Goth. inf. bindan (§ 303); Goth. OS. OHG. O.Icel. nam, he took, Goth. inf. niman (§ 305); Goth. OS. O.Icel. gaf, OHG. gab, he gave, Goth. inf. giban (§ 307).
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div type="subsubchapter">
      <head>e</head>

      <div type="section" n="66">
        <p>
          § 66. Germanic e became i, as Goth. wigs, OE. OS. OHG. weg, O.Icel. vegr, way; Goth. hilms, OE. OS. OHG. helm, helm; Goth. swistar, OS. swestar, OHG. swester, sister; Goth. hilpan (§ 303), OE. OS. helpan, OHG helfan, to help; Goth. stilan (§ 306), OE. OS. OHG. stelan, O.Icel. stela, to steal; Goth. itan (§ 308), OE. OS. etan, OHG. eȥȥan, O.Icel. eta, to eat.
        </p>

        <div type="note">
          <p>
            Note.—The stem-vowel in Goth. waíla (cp. OE. OS. wel, OHG. wela), well; and in Goth. aíþþáu (cp. OE. eþþa, oþþe, OHG. eddo, edo), or, has not yet been satisfactorily explained, in spite of the explanations suggested by various scholars.
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <pb n="27"/>
      <div type="section" n="67">
        <p>
          § 67. This i became broken to e (written aí) before r, h, and ƕ, as Goth. haírtō, OS. herta, OHG. herza, heart; Goth. aírþa, OS. ertha, OHG. erda, earth; Goth. waírþan (§ 303), OS. werthan, OHG. werdan, O.Icel. verða, to become; Goth. baíran (§ 305), OE. OS. OHG. beran, O.Icel. bera, to bear; Goth. raíhts, OS. OHG. reht, right; Goth. taíhun, OS. tehan, OHG. zehan, ten; Goth. saíƕan (§ 307), OS. OHG. sehan, to see.
        </p>

        <div type="note">
          <p>
            Note.—For nih, and not, from older *ni-ƕi = Lat. neque, we should expect *naíh, but the word has been influenced by the simple negative ni, not.
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div type="subsubchapter">
      <head>i</head>

      <div type="section" n="68">
        <p>
          § 68. Germanic i generally remained in Gothic, as Goth. fisks, OS. OE. fisc, OHG. fisk, O.Icel. fiskr, fish; Goth. widuwō, OE. widewe, OS. widowa, OHG. wituwa, widow; Goth. OE. OS. witan, OHG. wiȥȥan, O.Icel. vita, to know; Goth. nimiþ, OE. nimeþ, OS. nimid, OHG. nimit, he takes; Goth. bitum, OE. biton, OHG. biȥȥum, O.Icel. bitom, we bit, inf. Goth. beitan (§ 299), pp. Goth. bitans, OE. biten, OHG. gibiȥȥan, O.Icel. bitenn; Goth. bidjan, OE. biddan, O.Icel. biðja, OS. biddian, OHG. bitten, to pray, beg, entreat. See § 60.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div type="section" n="69">
        <p>
          § 69. Germanic i became broken to e (written aí) before r, h, ƕ, as Goth. baíriþ, OS. birid, OHG. birit, he bears, cp. § 60 (2), Goth. inf. baíran; Goth. maíhstus, OHG. mist (from *mihst), dunghill, cp. Mod. English dial. mixen; Goth. ga-taíhun, they told, OE. tigon, OHG. zigun, they accused, Goth. inf. ga-teihan (§ 299), pp. Goth. taíhans, OE. tigen, OHG. gi-zigan; Goth. laíƕum, OE. -ligon, OHG. liwum, we lent, inf. Goth. leiƕan (§ 299), pp. Goth. laíƕans, OE. -ligen, OHG. giliwan, OS. -liwan.
        </p>

        <div type="note">
          <p>
            Note.—On the forms hiri, hirjats, hirjiþ, see note to Mark xii. 7.
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>
    <pb n="28"/>
    <div type="subsubchapter">
      <head>o</head>

      <div type="section" n="70">
        <p>
          § 70. Germanic o became u, as Goth. juk, OHG. joh, OE. geoc, yoke; Goth. guþ, OE. OS. god, OHG. got, god; Goth. huzd, OS. hord, OHG. hort, treasure; pp. Goth. budans, OE. geboden, OS. gibodan, OHG. gibotan, O.Icel. boðenn, inf. Goth. biudan (§ 301), to offer; Goth. pp. hulpans, OE. geholpen, OS. giholpan,OHG. giholfan, Goth. inf. hilpan (§ 303), to help; pp. Goth. numans, OHG. ginoman, Goth. inf. niman (§ 305), to take. See § 62.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div type="section" n="71">
        <p>
          § 71. The u, which arose from Germanic o (§ 70), became broken to o (written aú) before r and h, as Goth. waúrd, OE. OS. word, OHG. wort, word; Goth. daúhtar, OE. dohtor, OS. dohtar, OHG. tohter, daughter; pp. Goth. taúhans, OE. getogen, OS. -togan, OHG. gizogan, O.Icel. togenn, Goth. inf. tiuhan (§ 301), to lead; Goth. waúrhta, OE. worhte, OHG. worhta, he worked, inf. Goth. waúrkjan, OHG. wurken; pp. Goth. waúrþans, OE. geworden, OS. giwordan, OHG. wortan, O.Icel. orðenn, Goth. inf. waírþan (§ 303), to become; pp. Goth. baúrans, OE. geboren, OS. OHG. giboran, O.Icel. borenn, inf. Goth. baíran (§ 305), to bear; Goth. ga-daúrsta, OE. dorste, OS. gi-dorsta, OHG. gi-torsta, he dared; inf. Goth. ga-daúrsan (§ 335).
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div type="subsubchapter">
      <head>u</head>

      <div type="section" n="72">
        <p>
          § 72. Germanic u generally remained in Gothic, as Goth. juggs, OS. OHG. jung, young; Goth. hunds, OE. OS. hund, O.Icel. hundr, OHG. hunt, dog, hound; Goth. sunus, OE. OS. OHG. sunu, son; Goth. hugjan, OS. huggian, OHG. huggen, to think; Goth. budum, OE. budon, OS. budun, OHG. butum, O.Icel. buðom, we offered, announced, inf. Goth. biudan (§ 301); Goth. bundum, OE. bundon, OS. bundun, OHG. buntum, O.Icel. bundom, we bound, Goth. inf. bindan (§ 303), pp. Goth. bundans,<pb n="29"/>OE. gebunden, OS. gibundan, OHG. gibuntan, O.Icel. bundenn. See § 40.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div type="section" n="73">
        <p>
          § 73. Germanic u became broken to o (written aú) before r and h, as Goth. saúhts, OS. OHG. suht, Germanic stem suhti-, sickness; Goth. waúrms, OS. OHG. wurm, OE. wyrm, stem wurmi-, serpent, worm; Goth. waúrkjan, OHG. wurken, to work; Goth. waúrþun, OE. wurdon, OS. wurdun, OHG. wurtun, O.Icel. urðo, they became, Goth. inf. waírþan (§ 303); Goth. taúhun, OE. tugon, OHG. zugun, they drew, pulled; Goth. inf. tiuhan (§ 301).
        </p>

        <div type="note">
          <p>
            Note.—u was not broken to aú before r which arose from older s by assimilation, as ur-runs, a running out; ur-reisan, to arise (§ 175 note 3). It is difficult to account for the u in the enclitic particle -uh, and; and in the interrogative particle nuh, then.
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>

  <div type="subchapter" n="2">
    <head>B. The Long Vowels of Accented Syllables</head>

    <div type="subsubchapter">
      <head>ā</head>

      <div type="section" n="74">
        <p>
          § 74. The ā, which arose from a according to § 59, remained in Gothic, as hāhan, to hang; faúrahāh (faúrhāh), curtain, veil, lit. that which hangs before; gahāhjō (av.), in order, connectedly; brāhta, he brought, inf. briggan; gafāhs, a catch, haul, related to gafāhan, to seize; fram-gāhts, progress, related to gaggan, to go; þāhō, clay; unwāhs, blameless.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div type="subsubchapter">
      <head>ǣ</head>

      <div type="section" n="75">
        <p>
          § 75. Germanic ǣ (= OE. ǣ, OS. OHG. O.Icel. ā) became ē in Gothic, as Goth. ga-dēþs, OE. dǣd, OS. dād, OHG. tāt, deed; Goth. mana-sēþs, multitude, world, lit. man-seed, OE. sǣd, OS. sād, OHG. sāt, seed; Goth. ga-rēdan, to reflect upon, OE. rǣdan, OS. rādan, OHG. rātan, O.Icel. rāða, to advise; Goth. bērum, OE. bǣron,<pb n="30"/>OS. OHG. bārum, O.Icel. bārom, we bore, Goth. inf. baíran (§ 305); Goth. sētun, OE. sǣton, OS. sātun, OHG. sāȥun, O.Icel. sāto, they sat, Goth. inf. sitan (§ 308).
        </p>
      </div>

      <div type="section" n="76">
        <p>
          § 76. The Germanic combination ǣj became ǣ (written ai, the long vowel corresponding to aí) in Gothic before vowels. This ai was a long open e-sound like the ǣ in OE. slǣpan or the vowel sound in English their. It occurs in very few words: as Goth. saian, OE. sāwan, OS. sāian, OHG. sāen, O.Icel. sā, to sow; Goth. waian, OE. wāwan, OHG. wāen (wājen), to blow; Goth. faianda, they are blamed. But in unaccented syllables the combination -ǣji- became -ái-, as habáis, thou hast, habáiþ, he has, from prim. Germanic *χaҌǣjizi, *χaҌǣjiđi.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div type="subsubchapter">
      <head>ē</head>

      <div type="section" n="77">
        <p>
          § 77. Germanic ē, which cannot be traced back phonologically to Indo-Germanic ē (§ 43), is of obscure origin. In Gothic the two sounds fell together in ē, but in the other Germanic languages they are kept quite apart, cp. §§ 43, 75.
        </p>

        <p>
          Germanic ē appears in Gothic as ē (OE. OS. O.Icel. ē, OHG. ē, later ea, ia, ie). In Goth. it occurs in a few words only, as Goth. OE. OS. O.Icel. hēr, OHG. hēr (hear, hiar, hier), here; Goth. fēra, OHG. fēra (feara, fiara), country, region, side, part; Goth. mēs, OE. mēse (mȳse), OHG. meas (mias), table, borrowed from Lat. mēnsa. Cp. § 5.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div type="subsubchapter">
      <head>ī</head>

      <div type="section" n="78">
        <p>
          § 78. Germanic ī, written ei in Gothic, remained, as Goth. swein, OE. OS. OHG. swīn, O.Icel. svīn, pig, cp. Lat. su-īnu-s, pertaining to a pig; Goth. ƕeila, a while, time, season, OE. hwīl, a while OS. hwīla (hwīl), time, OHG. wīla (hwīl), time, hour, O.Icel. hvīl, place of rest; Goth. seins, OE. OS. OHG. sīn, his; Goth. steigan<pb n="31"/>(§ 300), OE. OS. OHG. stīgan, O.Icel. stīga, to ascend. Cp. §§ 5, 6, 44, 48.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div type="subsubchapter">
      <head>ō</head>

      <div type="section" n="79">
        <p>
          § 79. Germanic ō remained in Gothic, as Goth. fōtus, OE. OS. fōt, OHG. fuoȥ, O.Icel. fōtr, foot, cp. Gr. Doric πώς; Goth. flōdus, OE. OS. flōd, OHG. fluot, O.Icel. fìōð, flood, stream; Goth. brōpar, O.Icel. brōðir, OE. brōpor, OS. brōðer, OHG. bruoder, brother; Goth. OE. OS. O.Icel. fōr, OHG. fuor, I fared, went, Goth. inf. faran (§ 309). Cp. §§ 42, 45.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div type="section" n="80">
        <p>
          § 80. The Germanic combination ōw became a long open o-sound (written au) before vowels, as Goth. sauil, sun, cp. OE. O.Icel. Lat. sōl; Goth. staua, (masc.) judge, (fem.) judgment, stauida, I judged (inf. stōjan), cp. Lithuanian stovéti, to stand, O.Bulgarian staviti, to place; taui (gen. tōjis), deed; afdauidai, pp. masc. nom. pl. exhausted, inf. *afdōjan.
        </p>

        <p>
          Here probably belong also bauan, to inhabit, OE. OHG. būan, to till, dwell; bnauan, to rub; trauan, OHG. trūēn, OS. trūōn, to trow, trust.
        </p>
      </div>

      <div type="section" n="81">
        <p>
          § 81. The Germanic combination ōwj became ōj, as stōja, I judge, from *stōwjō, older *stōwijo; tōjis (from *tōwjis), gen. sing. of taui, deed.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div type="subsubchapter">
      <head>ū</head>

      <div type="section" n="82">
        <p>
          § 82. Germanic ū remained in Gothic, as Goth. hūs (in gud-hūs, temple), OE. OS. OHG. O.Icel. hūs, house; Goth. rūms, OE. OS. OHG. O.Icel. rūm, room, related to Lat. rū-s (gen. rū-ris), open country; Goth. þūsundi, OE. þūsend, OS. thūsundig, OHG. dūsunt, O.Icel. þūsund, thousand; Goth. fūls, OE. OHG. fūl, O.Icel. fūll, foul; Goth. ga-lūkan, to shut, close, OE. lūcan, OHG. lūhhan, O.Icel. lūka, to lock.
        </p>

        <p>
          On the ū in forms like pūhta, it seemed, appeared;<pb n="32"/>hūhrus, hunger; jūhiza, younger;
          ūhtwō, early morn, see § 62.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>

  <div type="subchapter" n="3">
    <head>C. The Diphthongs of Accented Syllables</head>

    <div type="subsubchapter">
      <head>ai</head>

      <div type="section" n="83">
        <p>
          § 83. Germanic ai (OE. ā, OS. ē, OHG. ei (ē), O.Icel. ei) remained in Gothic, as Goth. áins, OE. ān, OS. ēn, OHG. ein, O.Icel. einn, one; Goth. háils, OE. hāl, OS. hēl, OHG. heil, hale, whole, sound; Goth. stáins, OE. stān, OS. stēn, OHG. stein, O.Icel. steinn, stone; Goth. stáig, OE. stāg, OS. stēg, OHG. steig, he ascended, Goth. inf. steigan (§ 300); Goth. háitan (§ 313), OE. hātan, OS. hētan, OHG. heiȥan, O.Icel. heita, to name, call. Cp. §§ 47, 49.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div type="subsubchapter">
      <head>au</head>

      <div type="section" n="84">
        <p>
          § 84. Germanic au (OE. ēa, OS. ō, OHG. ou (ō), O.Icel. au) remained in Gothic, as Goth. áugō, OE. ēage, OS. ōga, OHG. ouga, O.Icel. auga, eye; Goth. háubiþ (gen. háubidis), OE. hēafod, OS. hōҌid, OHG. houbit, O.Icel. haufuþ, head; Goth. dáupus, OE. dēað, OS. dōth, OHG. tōd, death; Goth. ráuþs, O.Icel. rauðr, OE. rēad, OS. rōd, OHG. rōt, red; Goth. gáumjan, to perceive, observe, OS. gōmian, OHG. goumen, to pay attention to; Goth. -hláupan, OE. hlēapan, OS. -hlōpan, OHG. louffan, O.Icel. hlaupa, to leap, run; pret. 1, 3 sing. Goth. káus, OE. cēas, OS. OHG. kōs, O.Icel. kaus, inf. Goth. kiusan (§ 302), to choose. Cp. §§ 50, 52.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div type="subsubchapter">
      <head>iu</head>

      <div type="section" n="85">
        <p>
          § 85. The iu, which arose from older eu (§ 63), remained in Gothic, as Goth. niujis, OS. OHG. niuwi, stem *niuja-, older *neujo-, new; Goth. stiurei (in us-stiurei, excess, riot), cp. OHG. stiurī, greatness, magnificence; Goth. kiusiþ, OS. kiusid, OHG. kiusit, he chooses, tests; Goth.<pb n="33"/>liuhtjan, OS. liuhtian, OHG. liuhten, to light; Goth. stiurjan, to establish, OHG. stiuren, to support, steer.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div type="subsubchapter">
      <head>eu</head>

      <div type="section" n="86">
        <p>
          § 86. eu (OE. ēo, OS. OHG. io(eo), O.Icel. jō(jū)) became iu in Gothic, as Goth. diups, OE. dēop, OS. diop, OHG. tiof, O.Icel. djūpr, deep; Goth. liuhaþ, OE. lēoht, OS. OHG. lioht, a light, cp. Gr. λευκός, light, bright; Goth. liufs, OE. lēof, OS. liof, OHG. liob, O.Icel. ljūfr, dear; Goth. tiuhan (§ 301), OS. tiohan, OHG. ziohan, to draw, pull; Goth. fra-liusan, OE. for-lēosan, OS. far-liosan, OHG. fìr-liosan, to lose.
        </p>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
